Guide to the Alsop Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alsop family papers
1734-1986
MS 34
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
44.75
(64 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, legal papers, diaries, estate records, account books, notebooks, deeds, and miscellanea of the Alsop family of Middletown, Connecticut. Several generations of family members are represented in the papers including: Joseph Wright Alsop (1772-1844), Joseph Wright Alsop (1804-1878), Joseph Wright Alsop (1838-1891), Joseph Wright Alsop (1876-1953), Mary Alsop Oliver Alsop (1815-1893), Richard Alsop (1726-1776), Richard Alsop (1789-1842), Charles Richard Alsop (1802-1865), and John De Koven Alsop (1879-1926). Family mercantile interests in Connecticut and related operations in Bolivia, Chile, and Peru are documented. Files relating to a legal case involving the firm of Alsop & Company, the United States government, and the governments of Bolivia and Chile (1865-1914) are included. The personal papers of several family members are also arranged in the papers.
Alsop family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John De Koven Alsop, Joseph E. Alsop, Mrs. Peggy Chubb, and Mrs. Stuart Farquhar in 1948; gift of Mrs. Kenneth MacKenzie and others, 1950-1956; gift of John Alsop, 1987; transfer from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 2011; gift of Joseph W. Alsop, 2013.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and three additions: I. Correspondence, 1776-1912. II. Alsop Claim Case, 1865-1914. III. Family Papers, 1752-1909. IV. Deeds and Miscellanea, 1734-1909. Additional material is arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Alsop was born in Middletown, Connecticut, on January 23, 1761. He studied at Yale College and became a notable literary figure. Alsop formed the "Hartford Wits," a literary group with members including Theodore Dwight, Lemuel Hopkins, and Benjamin Trumbull. He was principla writer for the "Echo," a series of satirical essays on political and social topics published as a volume in 1807. Alsop died in Flatbush, Long Island on August 20, 1815.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, legal papers, diaries, estate records, account books, notebooks, deeds, and miscellanea of the Alsop family of Middletown, Connecticut. Several generations of family members are represented in the papers including: Joseph Wright Alsop (1772-1844), Joseph Wright Alsop (1804-1878), Joseph Wright Alsop (1838-1891), Joseph Wright Alsop (1876-1953), Mary Alsop Oliver Alsop (1815-1893), Richard Alsop (1726-1776), Richard Alsop (1789-1842), Charles Richard Alsop (1802-1865), and John De Koven Alsop (1879-1926). Family mercantile interests in Connecticut and related operations in Bolivia, Chile, and Peru are documented. Files relating to a legal case involving the firm of Alsop & Company, the United States government, and the governments of Bolivia and Chile (1865-1914) are included. The personal papers of several family members are also arranged in the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Architecture, Domestic -- Designs and plans; Architecture, Domestic -- Connecticut; Architecture; Art; Business; Families; Governors -- Election; Working class; Law; Medicine; Popular culture; Students; Travelers -- United States; Women; Africa; Asia; Avon (Conn.); Bolivia -- Foreign economic relations -- United States; Chile -- Commerce; Connecticut -- Commerce; Connecticut; Europe -- Description and travel; Europe; Latin America; New England; Peru -- Commerce; United States -- Foreign economic relations -- Bolivia; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; West (U.S.); West Indies; Account books; Deeds; Diaries; Drawings (visual works); Essays; Poems; Recipes; Labor movement; Labor; Alsop, Aimee Elizabeth, 1870-; Alsop, Corinne Robinson, 1886-1971; Alsop, Elizabeth Winthrop Beach, 1847-1889; Alsop, Elizabeth Winthrop, 1874-1892; Alsop, Frances Maria, 1787-1866; Alsop, Francis Johonnot Oliver, 1881-1946; Alsop, Francis O.; Alsop, John De Koven, 1879-1926; Alsop, John, 1776-1841; Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1772-1844; Alsop, J. W. (Joseph Wright), 1804-approximately 1878; Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1838-1891; Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1876-1953; Alsop, Lucy Chauncey; Alsop, Lucy Whittlesey, 1773-1844; Alsop, Mary Alsop Oliver, 1815-; Alsop, Mary Wright, 1740-1829; Alsop, Richard, 1789-1842; Capt, Elizabeth Miller Langdon; Capt, John Samuel, d. 1832; Chauncey, Egisto Fabbri, 1874-1963; Chauncey, Elihu, 1779-1847; Clifford, John H. (John Henry), 1809-1876; Cryder, Helen Chauncey; Cushing, Tom, 1879-1941; Dabney, Charles William, 1794-1871; Dabney, Susan Heard Oliver, 1819-; Dana, Maria Wyllys Pomeroy Alsop, 1767-1861; Draper, Ruth, 1884-1956; Duval, William B., 1806-; Farley, Joseph; Gilbert, Aimee E. A. Alsop; Heard, Susan Oliver, 1780-; Hubbard, Sarah Williams; Jackson, Charles Eben, 1849-; Jackson, Eben, 1877-; Jackson, Edward Quintard, 1875-; Jackson, Robert Fenwick, 1877-; Leffingwell, Catharine Beatty Alsop, 1835-; Longworth, Alice Roosevelt, 1884-1980; Mason, Norman Howell; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1826-1885; Mütter, Mary Wright Alsop, 1815-1877; Oliver, Francis Eben, 1813-1850; Oliver, Francis Johonnot, 1777-1858; Oliver, George Stuart Johonnot, 1831-1904; Pomeroy, Elizabeth, 1784-1844; White, Eunice Pomeroy Bassett, 1776-; White, Percy Gardiner, 1878-1906; Whittelsey, Lucy Wetmore, 1748-1826; Worthington, Asa; Alsop family; Chauncey family; Oliver family; Morrison, Cryder & Co; Republican Party (Conn.); Russell & Co; Wetmore & Co; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1776-1912; Series I; 4 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged alphabetically by the name of the recipient.
  - Alsop, Aimee E.
    - General, 1821-1827; 1889-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Beach, Helen, 1890-1897 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Dabney, Roxanne, 1883-1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alsop, Charles, 1821-1885 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alsop, Elizabeth W., 1886-1889 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Alsop, Fanny, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alsop, Frances Maria, 1802-1815 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alsop, Francis J.O.
    - Alsop, Aimee E., 1890-1909 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1891-1907 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Alsop, Francis O., 1891-1909 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Alsop, Henry W., 1881; 1894-1896 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Alsop, John, 1793; 1802-1835 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Alsop, John De Koven
    - General, 1842-1908 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Alsop, Aimee E., 1887-1909, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-33)
  - Alsop, Joseph W. (1772-1844), 1790-1826 (Box 3, Folder 34-37)
  - Alsop, Joseph W. (1838-1891), 1866; 1886
    - General, 1850-1891 (Box 3, Folder 38-45)
    - Alsop, Aimee E., 1886-1891 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Children, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Parents, 1866-1867 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
  - Alsop, Joseph W. (1876-)
    - Alsop, Aimee E., 1886-1900 (Box 3, Folder 50-53)
    - Alsop, Aimee E., 1900-1909, undated (Box 4, Folder 54-56)
    - Alsop, Elizabeth W., 1891 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Alsop, John De Koven, 1895-1910 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Beach, Helen, 1892-1897 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Alsop, Joseph W., Jr. (1804-1878), 1824-1845 (Box 4, Folder 60-65)
  - Alsop, Lucy Whittelsey, 1822-1839 (Box 4, Folder 66-68)
  - Alsop, Mary Wright (1740-1829), 1789, 1797-1821 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Alsop, Mary (1762-1855), 1788, 1819, 1840, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Alsop, Mary (Oliver) (1815-1900), 1824-1835, 1883, 1891, undated (Box 4, Folder 71-72)
  - Alsop, Mary (Oliver) (1815-1900), 1830-1831, 1834-1841 (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
  - Alsop, Natalie (Hooper), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Alsop, Richard (1785-1842)
    - John Alsop, 1766 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Alsop & Co. NY, 1839 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Frances M. Alsop, 1806-1819 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Mary Alsop, 1801, 1817 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Samuel W. Dana, 1820 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Frances J. Oliver, 1819-1840 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Mary C. (Alsop) Oliver, 1816, 1818 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Elizabeth Pomeroy, 1820 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Frances Alsop (Pomeroy) Dabney, 1820 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Frederic Pomeroy, 1818-1820 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Richard Alsop (father), 1811 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Samuel Russel, 1838 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Maria W. (Pomeroy) Alsop Dana, 1822 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Alsop, Sara B., 1894 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Alsop, Susan, 1853 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - A - Au, 1805-1886 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Atwater, Wilber Olin, 1878, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Ba - Ch (Box 6, Folder 93-97)
  - Capt, John S., 1809-1831 (Box 6, Folder 98-100)
  - Ch - Co (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Chauncey, Egisto Fabri, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Chaucey, Elibu, 1815-1825 (Box 6, Folder 103-104)
  - Clifford, John Henry, 1899-1902 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Co - Cr (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Cu (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Cushing, Charles C., 1902-1905, undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Da - De (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Dabney, Charles W., 1794-1871, 1847, 1854, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Dabney, Susan Heard (Oliver), 1830, 1888, undated (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Dana, Maria Wyllys (Demeroy? may be Pomeroy?), 1799, 1811, undated (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - De - Dw (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - De Koven, John, 1872, 1878-1890 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Duval, William B., 1826-1828 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - E - Ho (Box 7, Folder 116-120)
  - Heard, Augustine (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Heard, Susan (Oliver), 1804, 1821, 1845, 1850, undated (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Ho - Hu (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Hubbard, Louis De Koven, 1856, 1861-1862 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Hubbard, Sarah (Williams), 1797-1806 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Hu (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Ja - Jo, 1776-1890 (Box 8, Folder 127-128)
  - Jackson, Charles Ebenezer (1849-), 1878-1912 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Jackson, Ebenezer (1877-) to Alsop, Aimee E., 1897-1909 (Box 8, Folder 130-131)
  - Jackson, Ebenezer Jr. (1796-), 1838, 1874, 1819 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - Jackson, Edward Quintard (1875-) to Alsop, Aimee E., 1896-1909 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Jackson, Robert Fenwick (1877-) to Alsop, Aimee E., 1896-1909 (Box 8, Folder 134-136)
  - K -Le, 1839-1891 (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - Li-Ly, 1824-1894 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - McC - McM, 1866-1887 (Box 8, Folder 139)
  - McClellan, George Brunton (1826-1885), 1861-1874 (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - McN - May, 1815-1890 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Mason, Norman Howell (1879-1942) to Alsop, Aimee E., 1899-1906 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Me - Mo, 1808-1908 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Mu - N, 1831-1903 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Morrison Cryder & Co. to Francis J. Oliver, 1838-1839 (Box 9, Folder 145-146)
  - Mutter, Mary Wright (Alsop)
    - Mary Alsop (Oliver), 1858 (Box 9, Folder 147)
    - Joseph Wright Alsop, Jr., 1836 (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - Joseph Wright Alsop, Sr., 1832, 1835 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Oa - Oz, 1802-1907 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Oliver, Francis Eben
    - Mary A. (Oliver) Alsop, Susan Heard (Oliver) Dabney, 1829, 1836, 1847 (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - Maria Wyllys (Pomeroy) Alsop Dana, Mary W. (Alsop) Mutter, 1833, 1848-1849 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - Francis J. Oliver, 1821-1845 (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - Mary Charlotte (Jackson) Oliver, 1828-1847 (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - Samuel Whittelsey Dana, 1826 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - Oliver, Francis Johonnat
    - Richard Alsop, 1820, 1832, 1837-1840 (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - Joseph Farley, 1833-1836 (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - Susan (Oliver) Heard, 1801-1804 (Box 9, Folder 158)
    - Overand Garney and Company, 1838-1840 (Box 9, Folder 159)
    - Miscellanea, 1797-1857 (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - Oliver, George S.J.
    - Joseph Wright Alsop, 1877-1891 (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - Aimee E. Alsop, 1898-1904 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Aimee E. Alsop, 1891-1898 (Box 10, Folder 163)
    - Francis Johonnat Oliver, 1850-1858 (Box 10, Folder 164)
    - Miscellanea, 1842-1904 (Box 10, Folder 165)
  - Pa - Pe, 1802-1873 (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - Pi - Po, 1779-1890 (Box 10, Folder 167)
  - Po - Q, 1784-1891 (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - Pomeroy, Elizabeth, 1805-1843 (Box 10, Folder 169)
  - R - S (Box 10, Folder 170)
  - S-T (Box 10, Folder 171)
  - T-V (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - Russel Manufacturing Company, 1861; 1886 (Box 10, Folder 173-174)
  - Saltonstall, Leverett, 1845-1846, undated (Box 10, Folder 175)
  - W - Z, 1786-1912 (Box 11, Folder 176-177)
  - White, Eunice (Pomeroy) Basset, 1856-1868 (Box 11, Folder 178)
  - White, Percy Gardiner, 1878-1906 (Box 11, Folder 179)
  - Whittelsey, Lucy (Wetmore), 1783-1798 (Box 11, Folder 180)
  - Williams, Robert, 1776, October 1 (Box 11, Folder 181)
  - Worthington, A., 1838-1840 (Box 11, Folder 182)
- Alsop Claim Case, 1865-1914; Series II; 2.50 linear feet (6 boxes)
  This series contains files arranged in chronological order. A report to President Roosevelt (1907 Aug-Sep) is filed after material for 1907 Jan-Dec.
  - 1865-1887, 1892 - 1904 March (Box 12, Folder 183-196)
  - 1904 April - 1906 November (Box 13, Folder 197-210)
  - 1907 January - December (Box 14, Folder 211-216)
  - 1907 August - Sep; Report to President Roosevelt (Box 14, Folder 217)
  - 1908 January - 1909 August (Box 14, Folder 218-222)
  - 1909 September - 1911 October (Box 15, Folder 223-235)
  - 1911 November - 1913 February (Box 16, Folder 236-248)
  - 1913 March - 1914 March (Box 17, Folder 249-262)
- Family Papers, 1752-1909; Series III; 9 linear feet (20 boxes)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual. For each individual, material is arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - Alsop, Aimee E.
    - Bills and receipts, 1901-1909, undated (Box 18, Folder 263)
    - Catalogs of books, undated (Box 18, Folder 264-265)
    - Will, 1868 (Box 18, Folder 269)
  - Alsop, Charles R.
    - Commonplace book, undated (Box 18, Folder 270)
    - Compositions, 1815-1818 (Box 18, Folder 271)
    - Diaries, 1825-1830, 1861-1865 (Box 18, Folder 272-274)
    - Essay, 1827 (Box 18, Folder 275)
    - Essay, undated (Box 19, Folder 276)
    - Expense books, 1818-1867 (Box 19, Folder 277-279)
    - Lectures, 1827 (Box 19, Folder 280)
    - Letters, 1827-1829 (Box 19, Folder 281)
    - Letters, 1828-1829, 1838-1841 (Box 20, Folder 282-283)
    - Manuscripts, 1897, undated (Box 20, Folder 284)
    - Notebooks, 1829-1830, 1856 (Box 20, Folder 285-286)
    - Poems, 1817-1830, 1820-1825 (Box 20, Folder 287-289)
    - Sketchbook, 1865 (Box 20, Folder 290)
  - Alsop, Clara P.
    - Diary, 1881 (Box 21, Folder 291)
    - Estate Papers
      - Account book, 1894-1897 (Box 21, Folder 292)
      - Carrington Gift, Tomb, 1894, 1895 (Box 21, Folder 293)
      - Checkbook, 1893-1897 (Box 21, Folder 294)
      - Checks, 1894-1899 (Box 21, Folder 295)
      - Conservator's papers
        - Accounts, 1895-1896 (Box 21, Folder 296)
        - Letters, 1893-1896 (Box 21, Folder 297-301)
        - Letters, 1893-1895 (Box 22, Folder 302)
        - Notebooks, 1894 (Box 22, Folder 303)
        - Papers, 1881-1894 (Box 22, Folder 304-305)
    - Household items, 1894-1896 (Box 22, Folder 306-309)
    - Ledger, 1894-1896 (Box 22, Folder 310)
    - Legacy: Alsop, J.W., undated (Box 22, Folder 311)
    - Legal judgements, 1894-1895 (Box 22, Folder 312)
    - Real estate, 1894-1895 (Box 22, Folder 313)
    - Receipts, 1894-1895, 1899 (Box 22, Folder 314)
    - Securities, 1896-1899 (Box 23, Folder 315)
    - Silver and jewelry, 1894-1904 (Box 23, Folder 316)
    - Waivers of heirs, 1896 (Box 23, Folder 317)
    - Wills; inventories, 1884-1894 (Box 23, Folder 318-319)
    - Miscellanea, 1893-1895 (Box 23, Folder 320)
  - Alsop, Frances M., 1863, 1866 (Box 23, Folder 321)
  - Alsop, Joseph Wright (1772-1844)
    - Estate Papers
      - Will, 1843-1857 (Box 23, Folder 322)
      - Miscellanea, 1824-1878 (Box 23, Folder 323-324)
      - Journal, 1809, July (Box 23, Folder 325)
      - Survey Bills, 1804-1805 (Box 23, Folder 326)
      - Miscellanea, 1799, 1816, 1833 (Box 23, Folder 327)
  - Alsop, Joseph Wright (1804-1878)
    - Account book, 1866-1877 (Box 24, Folder 328)
    - Bills and receipts, 1827-1865 (Box 24, Folder 329)
    - Daybook and journal, 1860-1866 (Box 24, Folder 330)
    - Ledgers, 1860-1877 (Box 25, Folder 331-332)
  - Alsop, Joseph Wright (1838-1891)
    - Account books, 1869-1873, 1878-1882
      General
      See: box 28, folders 353-354
    - Biography, 1892 (Box 26, Folder 333)
    - Diaries, 1856-1857, 1866-1867 (Box 26, Folder 334-335)
    - Estate
      - Checks and bankbooks, 1899-1914 (Box 26, Folder 336)
      - Journal A-Z, 1899-1914
        See: box 29, folder 356
      - Letters and papers, 1902-1907 (Box 26, Folder 337-341)
      - Memos, undated (Box 26, Folder 342)
      - Will and miscellanea, 1891-1901 (Box 26, Folder 343)
      - Miscellanea (Box 26, Folder 344)
    - Ledger, 1878-1883
      See: box 28, folder 355
  - Alsop, Joseph Wright (1838-1891)
    - Mastiff dogs, undated (Box 26, Folder 345)
    - Notebooks, 1876, 1878 (Box 26, Folder 346)
    - Notebooks, 1879-1880, 1884-1886, 1888-1890 (Box 27, Folder 347-349)
    - Steel engraving negative, undated (Box 27, Folder 350)
    - Writing books, undated (Box 27, Folder 351)
    - Miscellanea (Box 27, Folder 352)
    - Oversize
      - Accounts, 1869-1873, 1878-1882 (Box 28, Folder 353-354)
      - Journal, A-Z., 1899-1914 (Box 28, Folder 355)
      - Ledger, 1878-1883 (Box 29, Folder 356)
  - Alsop, J.W. and Son: ledger, 1830-1835 (Box 30, Folder 357)
  - Alsop, Mary (1762-1855)
    - Poems, 1786-1826, 1793, 1839-1841, 1852-1854 (Box 31, Folder 358-362)
    - Survey bill; engraving plate, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 363)
  - Alsop, Mary Oliver
    - Account book, 1868-1888 (Box 31, Folder 364)
    - Estate inventory, 1892 (Box 31, Folder 365)
  - Alsop, Richard
    - Business papers, 1810-1838 (Box 32, Folder 366)
    - Estate papers, 1768-1791 (Box 32, Folder 367)
    - Financial papers, 1786-1830 (Box 32, Folder 368)
  - Armstrong, Catherine: bible, 1804 (Box 32, Folder 369)
  - Armstrong, Thomas: account book, 1840-1848 (Box 32, Folder 370)
  - Barratt, John, 1752 (Box 32, Folder 371)
  - Beach, Hunn Carrington
    - Letterbooks, 1857 (Box 32, Folder 372)
    - Miscellanea, 1840-1863 (Box 32, Folder 373)
  - Dabney and Cunningham
    - Business papers, 1853-1864 (Box 32, Folder 374)
    - Maritime papers, 1853-1854, 1857-1864 (Box 33, Folder 375)
    - Miscellanea, 1853-1865 (Box 33, Folder 376)
  - Dabney, Charles W.
    - Essays, 1842 (Box 33, Folder 377)
    - Receipts, 1846-1847, 1850-1852 (Box 33, Folder 377a)
    - School papers, 1841-1848 (Box 33, Folder 377b)
  - Dabney, Francis and Roxanna, 1844-1845 (Box 33, Folder 377c)
  - Dabney, Susan H. Oliver: account book, 1879-1884 (Box 33, Folder 377)
  - Dana Maria: will, 1850 (Box 33, Folder 377e)
  - Dana, Samuel W.: Estate inventory, 1830 (Box 33, Folder 378)
  - Godemar, Freres et Capt., Invoices, 1818-1821 (Box 33, Folder 379)
  - Mutter, Mary Wright Alsop: notebook, 1825-1830 (Box 33, Folder 380)
  - Oliver, Anthony, 1767 (Box 33, Folder 381)
  - Oliver, Catherine Alsop
    - Account book, 1879-1889 (Box 34, Folder 382)
    - Financial papers, 1871-1876 (Box 34, Folder 383)
  - Oliver, Ebenezer J., 1825 (Box 34, Folder 384)
  - Oliver, Francis Ebenezer
    - Atlas, undated (Box 34, Folder 385)
    - Bills, 1845, 1846 (Box 34, Folder 386)
    - Diaries, 1828-1830, 1836 April-July 1846, January-May (Box 34, Folder 387-390)
    - Diaries, 1847-1849 (Box 35, Folder 391-393)
    - Drawings, 1847-1849 (Box 35, Folder 394-397)
    - Drawings, 1849, undated (Box 36, Folder 398-399)
    - Letterbooks, 1828-1830, 1832-1833, 1835-1836 (Box 36, Folder 400-401)
  - Oliver, Francis J.
    - Business papers, 1794, 1799-1838 (Box 36, Folder 402)
    - Conveyances, 1825-1837 (Box 36, Folder 403)
    - Estate papers, undated (Box 36, Folder 404)
    - Expense books, 1810-1820, 1817-1839 (Box 36, Folder 405-406)
    - Indentures, 1834-1837 (Box 36, Folder 407)
    - Tax records, 1827-1841 (Box 36, Folder 408)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 36, Folder 409)
  - Oliver, George Stuart J.
    - Drawing book, 1887 (Box 37, Folder 410)
    - Pictures, undated (Box 37, Folder 411)
  - Oliver: miscellanea (Box 37, Folder 412)
  - Perevia, Joao Souza Evangelista de, 1839 (Box 37, Folder 413)
  - Paxton, Charles, undated (Box 37, Folder 414)
  - Price, William: will, 1777 (Box 37, Folder 415)
  - Russel, Samuel: will, 1860 (Box 37, Folder 416)
  - Stuart, George: will, 1752 (Box 37, Folder 417)
  - Welmore, Hannah Edwards: journal, 1736-1739 (Box 37, Folder 418)
  - Wright, Joseph, 1743-1777 (Box 37, Folder 419)
  - Miscellanea (Box 37, Folder 420)
- Deeds and Miscellania, 1734-1909; Series IV; 3 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: Deeds and Miscellanea. Deeds is arranged alphabetically. Miscellanea is arranged alphabetically by record type and/or topic, with "Prices Current" filed at the end of the section.
  - Deeds
    - Alsop, 1800-1835 (Box 38, Folder 421)
    - A - B, 1758-1816 (Box 38, Folder 422)
    - C - D, 1734-1860 (Box 38, Folder 423)
    - E - G, 1746-1851 (Box 38, Folder 424)
    - H - J, 1750-1803 (Box 38, Folder 425)
    - K - M, 1764-1860 (Box 38, Folder 426)
    - N - P, 1734-1831 (Box 38, Folder 427)
    - R, 1764-1840 (Box 38, Folder 428)
    - S, 1789-1792 (Box 38, Folder 429)
    - T - W, 1760-1820 (Box 38, Folder 430)
  - Miscellanea
    - Alsop House Papers, 1870-1877, undated (Box 39, Folder 431)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 39, Folder 432)
    - Genealogy files, 1830-1890 (Box 39, Folder 433-437)
    - Guestbook, Calling Cards, 1889-1894 (Box 39, Folder 438)
    - Needlework, undated (Box 39, Folder 439)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1856-1909 (Box 40, Folder 440)
    - Photographs, 1894-1895, undated (Box 40, Folder 441-442)
    - Poems, undated (Box 40, Folder 443)
    - Recipes and Menus, 1872-1878 (Box 40, Folder 444)
    - Revolutionary War Orderly Book, 1777-1779 (Box 40, Folder 445)
    - Miscellanea (Box 40, Folder 446)
    - Prices Current, 1851-1854, 1861-1869 (Box 41, Folder 447-451)
  - Folio I (Box 42A–42C)
  - Certificates of Baptism, Marriage, etc., 1752-1872 (Box 44)
  - Alsop, Mary O. drawing book (Box 44)
  - Mary Alsop (Oliver) Alsop drawing book (number 2), 1825 (Box 44)
- Additional Material, Accession 1987-M-071
  - Family Papers, 1760-1986; Series I
    The addition carries the Alsop Family Papers into the twentieth century and primarily documents the lives of three family members and their presence in Connecticut state politics. Material on two of the family members, Corinne Robinson Alsop (1886-1971) and John Alsop (1915-2000), is only found in this addition.
    Joseph W. Alsop (1876-1953), known as "the Squire of Avon," was a member of the Yale Class of 1898 and a "gentleman farmer," raising cattle and tobacco on his farm, Wood Ford, in Avon. Mr. Alsop served as the first selectman from Avon for many years and as state representative from the town from 1907 to 1909. He also served as a state senator from 1909 to 1911.
    His wife, Corinne Robinson Alsop, was a niece of President Theodore Roosevelt and a cousin of Eleanor Roosevelt and Alice Roosevelt Longworth. She served on many Republican committees and formed the first group to give women recognition in the Connecticut Republican Party before they had won the right to vote. In 1924 she was elected to a two-year term in the Connecticut State House of Representatives, making her the first female Roosevelt to hold an elected office. Refusing to cross party lines to support her cousin Franklin Roosevelt's run for the presidency, Mrs. Alsop made the daring move to second the nomination of his opponent, Alf Landon, at the 1936 Republican National Convention.